Guide to the Rare Book and Manuscript Leaves Collection, 1400-1932 SC.1970.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Rare Book and Manuscript Leaves Collection
1300-1932
1400-1800
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh
SC.1970.01
4 Linear Feet (2 oversize boxes)
The Rare Book and Manuscript Leaves Collection is a teaching collection that illustrates the history of the book and printing and includes early examples of printing styles, paper, and enrichments.
Acquisition Information
The collection was a gift to the Elizabeth Nesbitt Room, which was located at the Information Sciences Library, until its closure in 2012. The leaves were gifted to the Nesbitt Room from various donors, namely University of Pittsburgh alumni who purchased the leaves from various booksellers. Some of the leaves include a note identifying the donor and year donated.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in six series according to when each leaf was created or published, and is organized chronologically within each series.
History
The leaves serve as a teaching collection that illustrates the history of the book and printing due to the variety of printing styles, enrichments, and paper. The collection contains leaves taken from a variety of manuscripts and books, including breviaries, books of hours, antiphonaries, and bibles.
The collection was originally housed at the Elizabeth Nesbitt Room, located at the Information Sciences Library, until its closure in 2012. The leaves were gifted to the Nesbitt Room from various donors, namely University of Pittsburgh alumni who purchased the leaves from various booksellers. Some of the leaves include a note identifying the donor and year donated.
Previous Citation
Rare Book and Manuscript Leaves Collection, 1400-1932, SC.1970.01, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Scope and Content Notes
The collection contains leaves taken from a variety of manuscripts and books, including breviaries, books of hours, antiphonaries, and bibles. A majority of the collection is from the 14th to 18th century and a number of languages are represented, namely Latin. The collection illustrates the history of the book and printing due to the variety of printing styles, paper, and enrichments, including decorated initials, rubrication, marginalia, handcolored woodblocks, historiated borders, and gothic type and the use of vellum.
Early printed books -- 17th century; Early printed books -- 16th century; Early printed books -- 15th century; Incunabula; Manuscripts, Medieval; University of Pittsburgh
- 14th and 15th Century, I.
  - Angeli Domini, 14th Century (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Content Notes
    An antiphon for Feast of St. Michael the Archangel.
    Size: 34 cm x 49.5
    Language: Latin
    Characteristics: Manuscript, printed on vellum, red and black ink
  - Leaf from a Breviary, 1425 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Description: Printed in Spain
    Size: 18.5 x 25.5 cm
    Language: Unknown
    Characteristics: Manuscript, two columns, rubrication, red and blue initials, printed on vellum
  - Canzoniere e Trionfi, Che fai alma?, 1473 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Four different poems from Canzoniere by Petrarch. Printed in Venice, Italy.
    Size: 28.4 x 18.2 cm
    Language: Italian
    Characteristics: Text in Roman typeface, rubricated initials hand written in red and blue, marginalia includes the bishop's hand
  - Arom Biblia Latina, Judith, 1478 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Description of the life of Judith printed by Reynsburch and Novimagio in Venice, Italy.
    Size: 20.5 x 31.5 cm
    Characteristics: Gothic type
  - Pre-Lutheran Middle High German Bible, 1480 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Bible printed in Augsburg, Germany by Anton Sorg.
    Size: 20 x 40 cm
    Language: German
    Characteristics: Handwritten decorated initials
  - Lives of the Saints, Brigitta, 1488 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Leaf from Jacobus de Varagine's Lives of the Saints. Printed in Germany.
    Size: 34.2 x 22.4 cm
    Characteristics: Gothic typeface, hand colored decorations in red
  - Nuremberg Chronicle (Liber Chronicarum),Das furft alter, 1493 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Bible and history of people related to the Bible printed by H. Schedel. Printed in Germany.
    Size: 43x30 cm
    Language: German or Latin
    Characteristics: Printed, handcolored woodblocks of Biblical figures, hand colored decorations
  - Nuremberg Chronicle (Liber Chronicarum), Sextas etas mudi..., 1493 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Information on Germanic kings: Henricus Septimus, Wilhelmus, and Conradus. Printed by H. Schedel in Germany.
    Language: Latin Characteristics: Printed, hand decorated initials, woodcuts of Germanic kings of the Interregnum
  - Die cronica van der hillger state can coellen, Germany, August 23, 1499 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Leaf printed by Johann Koelhoff (the younger) in Cologne, Germany.
    Size: 30.4 x 21.3 cm
    Language: Dutch
    Characteristics: Printed in Gothic typeface, woodcuts, paragraph-marks in red
  - Latin prayer book, laudate cum omns..., 15th Century (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Size: 14 x 19.5 cm
    Characteristics: Manuscript on vellum, illuminations, initials in gold leaf, red and blue ink
- 16th Century, II.
  - Psalms and liturgical text, in honore tuo..., Approximately 1500 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Printed in Paris, France by Thielmann Kerver
    Size: 17.7 x 11.3 cm
    Characteristics: Historiated borders, laid marks, rubrication, wood cuts, cursive type, red and black ink
  - Opera, Ducolicou augloga prima, 1502 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Virgil's Opera printed by Gruninger in Strausberg
    Size: 21 x 31 cm
    Language: Italian or Latin
    Characteristics: Marginalia, decorated initials
  - Te micht, Approximately 1500 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Printed by Vostre in Paris, France.
    Size: 11 x 17 cm, double sided
    Language: French or Latin
    Characteristics: historiated borders, printed on vellum
  - Flemish Book of Hours, Die ghetijden van onser liever vrouwen met vele schoone loven ende oracien, Rochticheit tenes ende, 1533 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Printed by Thielmann Kerver in Paris, France.
    Size: 16.4 x 10.4 cm
    Language: Flemish
    Characteristics: Printed, ornamented boarder, rubication, black and red ink
  - ad beatam virg, 1545 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Printed by Marcolini in Venice, Italy
    Size: 17.1 x 11.2 cm
    Characteristics: historiated borders, rubication
  - Latin Bible, Biblia Sacra Cvm Glossa Interlineari, Ordinaria, Et Nicolai Lyrani Postilla, eiufsdemque Moralitatibus, Burgensis Additionibus, & Thoringl Replicis, 1588 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Size: 26.5 x 42.5 cm
    Characteristics: Manicules
- 17th Century, III.
  - Greek Book of Religious Works, Vetus Tesamentum Ex Versione Septuaginta Interpretum, De Eleemos Et Collatione In Sanctos Ser XXII, 1610 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Book of religious works in Greek with Latin interpretation in right column
    Size: 22 x 35.5 cm
    Language: Greek and Latin
  - Matthaeu Polo. Synopsis Criticorum Aliorumque Sacrae Scripturae, Commentatorum en EZEC, 1678 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Interpretations on the Bible
    Size: 25.5 x 40 cm
  - Matthew Poole. Annotations Upon the Holy Bible, Jeremiah, 1696 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Description: Third Edition printed in London
    Size: 24 x 40 cm
    Language: English
- 18th Century, IV.
  - Leaf from a Farsi text, 18th Century (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Quote from Orientalia: "Illuminated leaf from an Eighteenth Century Persian manuscript of poems."
    Size: 11 x 18 cm
    Language: Farsi
    Characteristics: Manuscript with illumination
  - Cornelius A Lapide. E Societate Jesu, S. Scipturae Olim Lovanii, Postea Romae Professoris, Commentarius in Canticum Canticorum, Commentaria in Matthaum, 1725 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Comments on scriptures, law and prophets.
    Size: 22.5 x 36.5 cm
  - Augustin Calmet.Commentarium Literale In Omnees Ac Singulos Tum Veteris…, 1734 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    A page of comments on the Bible and Biblical law printed by Sebastiano Coleti
    Size: 20.5 x 30 cm
  - Samuel Ecclesiastes, in Cathedram Productus, Pro S. Benedicti Panegyrico, 1740 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Description: Original book from a monastary in Budapest, Hungary that was confiscated with other religious books.
    Size: 21.5 x 36.5 cm
  - Rapin de Thoyras.The History of England, 1747 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Size: 24 x 40 cm Language: English
  - Joseph Ignaz Claus. Spicilegium Catechetico-Concionatorium id est Conceptus Exegetici, De Judicio Circa Opera Bon, 1750 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Critical religious explainations on the Bible and other Catholic texts.
    Size: 19.6 x 33 cm
  - Francois-Aime Pouget. Institutiones Catholicae in Modum Catecheseos…, 1765 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Details the history and institutions of Catholicism.
    Size: 24 x 38 cm
  - Robert Bell's Book Auction catalog, 1778 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Facsimile of a broadside printed in Washington D.C. with commentary by James Gilreath.
    Size: 21.5 x 35.5 cm
  - Joanne Baptiste Conet. Clypeus Theologiae Thomisticaue, Quaft VIII De Ordine Charitatis inter proximos, 1794 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Printed in Antwerp.
    Size: 19.5 x 31.5 cm
  - Sheet of printer ornaments, 1798 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Sample of various printers ornamentations including vignettes; head-pieces; tail-pieces; alphabet in roman and italic type. Printed in France.
    Size: 37 X 44.5 cm
    Language: French
- 19th Century, V.
  - The Famous History Of the Learned Friar Bacon, Approximately 1800 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Page from the biography of Friar Roger Bacon. Printed in Bow-Church-Yard, London, England.
    Size: 8.5 x 17 cm
  - Declaration of Independence reprint from Harper's Weekly, 1858 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    A reprint of the Declaration of Independence from Harper's Weekly, July 3, 1858. Printed in New York, USA.
    Size: 56.5 x 40 cm
- 20th Century, VI.
  - JM Barrie. Farewell Miss Julie Logan, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    J.M. Barrie's final work of prose, published as a free supplement to The Times on Thursday December 24, 1931.
    Size: 31 x 47 cm
    Characteristics: Handmade paper wrappers.
  - Gutenberg Bible Facsimile, Gutenberg and the Book of Books, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    A reproduction of Psalm 23 from the Gutenberg Bible printed by William Edwin Rudge, New York 1932.
    Size: 29.5 x 40 cm
    Characteristics: Initials in blue and red ink
  - Le Journal de la Decoration, Motifs du Moyen-Age, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    A collection of illustrations by Willy Pogany. Printed in France.
    Size: 25 x 31.5 cm